Learning-SICP 学习小组
倾情制作
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
翻译&&时间轴
邓雄飞
（Dysprosium）
压制&&特效
邓雄飞
（Dysprosium）
校对
邓雄飞
特别感谢
裘宗燕教授
寄存机器
Register Machines
PROFESSOR: Well, up 'til now, I suppose,
教授：我认为 到目前为止
we've been learning about a lot of techniques for
我们已经学习了很多关于
organizing big programs, symbolic manipulation a bit,
组织程序以及操纵符号的技术
some of the technology that you use for establishing languages,
以及用来构建语言的技术
one in terms of another,
用一门语言去创建另一门语言
which is used for organizing very large programs.
这在组织大型程序时非常有用
In fact, the nicest programs I know
实际上 我所知的最好的程序
look more like a pile of languages
看起来更像是一堆语言
than like a decomposition of a problem into parts.
而不是将问题分解成若干部分
Well, I suppose at this point,
我想 此时此刻
there are still, however, a few mysteries
关于这类东西的工作方式
about how this sort of stuff works.
仍然存在一些谜团
And so what we'd like to do now is
因此 我现在需要
diverge from the plan of
偏离原先的计划
telling you how to organize big programs,
不再继续讲解如何组织大型程序
and rather tell you something about the mechanisms
而是告诉你一些关于
by which these things can be made to work.
使这些事情可以起作用的机制
The main reason for this is
这样做的主要是为了
demystification, if you will,
揭秘
that we have a lot of mysteries left,
剩下的很多谜团
like exactly how it is the case that a program is controlled,
比如说 如何控制程序的运行
how a computer knows what the next thing to do is,
计算机如何知晓下一步的动作
or something like that.
等等等等
And what I'd like to do now is make that clear to you
我现在就要让你们清楚地知道
that even if you've never played with a physical computer before,
就算你之前没有使用过计算机
the mechanism is really very simple,
但这种机制非常简单
and that you can understand it completely with no trouble.
你可以毫无问题地理解它
So I'd like to start by imagining that we--
好吧 我们先来想象一个 --
well, the way we're going to do this, by the way,
先说明一下 我们采用的方法是
is we're going to take some very simple Lisp programs,
把一些非常简单的Lisp程序
very simple Lisp programs,
真的非常简单
and transform them into hardware.
把它们转换成硬件
I'm not going to worry about some intermediate step
我不会考虑一些中间步骤
of going through some existing computer machine language
比如转换成某种现有的机器语言
and then showing you how that computer works,
然后来解释计算机是如何工作的
because that's not as illuminating.
因为那不太明显
So what I'm really going to show you
所以我真正要向你展示的是
is how a piece of machinery can be built
如何构建一台机器来完成
to do a job that you have written down as a program.
一项由你写的程序所描述的工作
That program is, in fact, a description of a machine.
而程序呢 实际上就是一个机器的描述
We're going to start with a very simple program,
我们从一个非常简单的程序开始
proceed to show you some simple mechanisms,
然后演示一些简单的机制
proceed to a few more complicated programs,
进而用更复杂的程序
and then later show you a not very complicated program,
然后又演示一个不那么复杂的程序
how the evaluator transforms into a piece of hardware.
来演示求值器是如何变成硬件的
And of course at that point,
当然 到那个时候
you have made the universal transition
你就有了通用的转换算法
and can execute any program imaginable
并且可以用一个定义明确的硬件
with a piece of well-defined hardware.
来执行任何可以想象的程序
Well, let's start up now,
那么 现在让我们开始
give you a real concrete feeling for this sort of thing.
给你们关于这些东西的具体感觉
Let's start with a very simple program.
我们先从一个非常简单的程序开始
Here's Euclid's algorithm.
这是欧几里得算法
It's actually a little bit more modern than Euclid's algorithm.
它实际上比欧几里德算法更现代一些
Euclid's algorithm for computing the greatest common divisor of two numbers
我想 用来计算两数最大公约数的欧几里得算法
was invented 350 BC, I think.
是在公元前350年发明的
It's the oldest known algorithm.
它是已知最古老的算法
But here we're going to talk about GCD of A and B,
我们先定义(GCD A B)
the Greatest Common Divisor or two numbers, A and B.
也就是用来计算A、B两数的最大公约数
And the algorithm is extremely simple.
这个算法相当简单
If B is 0,
如果B等于0
then the result is going to be A.
那么结果就是A
Otherwise, the result is the GCD of B
否则结果就是 (GCD B
and the remainder when A is divided by B.
(REMAINDER A B))
So this we have here is a very simple iterative process.
这里 我们定义了一个简单的迭代过程
This a simple recursive procedure,
这是一个简单的递归过程
recursively defined procedure, recursive definition,
也可以说这个过程是递归地定义的
which yields an iterative process.
但它产生的计算过程是迭代的
And the way it works is that every step,
它的原理是 在每一步
it determines whether B was zero.
判断B是否为0
And if B is 0, we got the answer in A.
如果B为0 那么A的值就是我们的答案
Otherwise, we make another step
否则就进入下一个步骤
where A is the old B,
其中A就变成旧的B
and B is the remainder of the old A divided by the old B.
而B的值 是A旧值除B旧值的余数
Very simple.
非常简单
Now this, I've already told you
现在 我已经通过这种方式
some of the mechanism by just saying it that way.
告诉了你一些机制
I said it in time.
我是按时序告诉你们的
I said there are certain steps,
我说 其中有特定的步骤
and that, in fact,
并且实际上
one of the things you can see here
你可以在这里知道
is that one of the reasons why this is iterative
为什么这个过程是迭代的
is nothing is needed of the last step to get the answer.
是因为最后一步无需额外信息来得到答案
All of the information that's needed to run this algorithm is in A and B.
所有运行此算法所需的信息都在A和B中
It has two well-defined state variables.
它有两个定义明确的状态变量
So I'm going to define a machine for you
现在 我就要给你们定义一台机器
can compute you GCDs.
用来计算GCD
Now let's see.
我们来看看
Every computer that's ever been made that's a single-process computer,
每台制造的计算机都是单进程计算机
as opposed to a multiprocessor of some sort,
而不是某种多处理器
is made according to the same plan.
都是按照相同的方案制定的
The plan is the computer has two parts,
这种方案就是：计算机由两部分组成
a part called the datapaths,
一部分叫数据通路
and a part called the controller.
而另一部分叫控制器
The datapaths correspond to a calculator that you might have.
数据通路相当于你可能有的计算器
It contains certain registers that remember things,
它有一些寄存器 能够存储数据
and you've all used calculators.
你们都用过计算器
It has some buttons on it and some lights.
它上面有一些按钮和指示灯
And so by pushing the various buttons,
通过按下不同的按钮
you can cause operations to happen inside there among the registers,
你可以使操作在寄存器内发生
and some of the results to be displayed.
并显示计算结果
That's completely mechanical.
它是完全机械式的
You could imagine that box has no intelligence in it.
你可以认为那个盒子没有任何智能
Now it might be very impressive that it can produce the sine of a number,
它能计算一个数的正弦也许令人吃惊
but that at least is apparently possibly mechanical.
但它显然是机械式的
At least, I could open that up in the same way I'm about to open GCD.
至少 我可以像打开GCD机器一样打开它
So this may have a whole computer inside of it,
也就是说 它其中可能有一整台计算机
but that's not interesting.
但这并不有趣
Addition is certainly simple.
加法相当简单
That can be done without any further mechanism.
不借助额外机制就可以完成
Now also, if we were to look at the other half, the controller,
现在 如果我们来看另外的一部分：控制器
that's a part that's dumb, too.
这一部分也非常简单
It pushes the buttons.
它负责按下按钮
It pushes them according to the sequence,
它根据指令序列来按按钮
which is written down on a piece of paper,
指令是写在纸上的
and observes the lights.
控制器还会观察指示灯
And every so often, it comes to a place in a sequence that says,
而且每隔一段 它就会来到指令序列中的一处
if light A is on, do this sequence.
如果指示灯A亮 则执行某段指令
Otherwise, do that sequence.
否则执行另外的指令
And thereby, there's no complexity there either.
因此 这其中也没有什么复杂的
Well, let's just draw that
那么 让我们来画一下
and see what we feel about that.
然后来感受一下它
So for computing GCDs,
为了计算GCD
what I want you to think about is that there are these registers.
你们要知道：这其中有一些寄存器
A register is a place where I store a number, in this case.
这里 寄存器就是一个存储数值的地方
And this one's called a.
这个寄存器存储的是A
And then there's another one for storing b.
而另外的这个存储的是B
Now we have to see what things we can do with these registers,
现在我们来看看 有了这些寄存器后能做什么
and they're not entirely obvious what you can do with them.
至于你能利用它做什么 并不是很明显
Well, we have to see what things we need to do with them.
那么 我们必须看看需要用它们做什么
We're looking at the problem we're trying to solve.
我们来看看尝试求解的问题
One of the important things for designing a computer,
计算机设计的一个要点就是
which I think most designers don't do,
我想大多数设计师都不会照做
is you stay the problem you want to solve
也就是专注于待解的问题
and then use what you learn from studying the problem you want to solve
然后使用你研究问题所学到的东西
to put in the mechanisms needed to solve it
把那些求解问题所需要的机制
in the computer you're building,
融入正在构建的计算机中
no more no less.
不多也不少
Now it may be that the problem you're trying to solve
现在 可能你所要解决的问题
is everybody's problem,
是大家共有的问题
in which case you have to build in a universal
这种情况下你需要构建
interpreter of some language.
某种语言的通用解释器
But you shouldn't put any more in than required
但是你添加的机制不能比
to build the universal interpreter of some language.
想构建的语言解释器的需求多
We'll worry about that in a second.
这一点 我们稍后来讨论
OK, going back to here, let's see.
好了 让我们回到这里
What do we have to be able to do?
我们必须能够做什么？
Well, somehow, we have to be able to get B into A.
首先 我们能把B的值赋给A
We have to be able to get the old value of B into the value of A.
我们要能够把B的旧值赋给A
So we have to have some path by which stuff can flow
因此 我们需要某种能够让数据流通的“路径”
whatever this information is,
而不管数据具体是什么
OK? from b to a.
从B到A的通路
I'm going to draw that with by an arrow
我箭头来指示
saying that it is possible to move the contents of b into a,
我们能够把B的值赋给A
replacing the value of a.
从而替换A的旧值
And there's a little button here which you push
当你按下这里的按钮后
which allows that to happen.
就能够实现这个效果
That's what the little x is here.
这个按钮就在这里
Now it's also the case
同样的
that I have to be able to compute the remainder of a and b.
我还需要能够计算A除B的余数
Now that may be a complicated mess.
这可能混乱而又复杂
On the other hand, I'm going to make it a small box.
但另一方面 我会把它放到一个小盒子中
If we have to, we may open up that box
如果有必要的话 我们可以打开那个盒子
and look inside and see what it is.
看看其中有些什么
So here, I'm going to have a little box,
这就是那个小盒子
which I'm going to draw this way,
我这么来画它
which we'll call the remainder.
我把它叫做REM
And it's going to take in a.
它接受A
That's going to take in b.
同时也要接受B
And it's going to put out something,
它有一个输出
the remainder of a divided by b.
也就是A除以B的余数
Another thing we have to see here is
在这里 我们同样需要能够
that we have to be able to test whether b is equal to 0.
判断B是否等于0
Well, that means somebody's got to be looking at--
也就是说 总得有个东西
a thing that's looking at the value of b.
去查询B的值
I have a light bulb here
这是一个指示灯
which lights up if b equals 0.
当B等于0时 它就会点亮
That's its job.
它就是干这个的
And finally, I suppose, because of the fact
最后 因为我们希望
that we want the new value of a to be the old value of b,
A的新值是B的旧值
and simultaneously the new value of b to be something I've done with a,
同时B的新值是有关于A的
and if I plan to make my machine
如果我打算让机器
such that everything happens one at a time,
一次只发生一件事
one motion at a time,
一次执行一个动作
and I can't put two numbers in a register,
并且我不能在一个寄存器中放两个数字
then I have to have another place to put one while I'm interchanging.
那么进行互换时 必须有另外的地方放置一个数字
OK?
对吧？
I can't interchange the two things in my hands,
我不能同时交换两手的东西
unless I either put two in one hand
除非我一手拿两个
and then pull it back the other way,
然后从中取另外一个
or unless I put one down,
或者我先放下一个
pick it up, and put the other one, like that
取得另一个后再像这样捡起来
unless I'm a juggler,
除非我是耍杂技的
which I'm not, as you can see,
当然正如大家所见 我并不是
in which case I have a possibility of timing errors.
这种情况下 我就会遇到时序错误
In fact, much of the type of computer design
事实上 人们所做的许多类型的计算机设计
people do involves timing errors,
都遇到了时序错误
of some potential timing errors,
或者潜在的时序错误
which I don't much like.
我不太喜欢这种错误
But. So for that reason,
因此 出于这个原因
I have to have a place to put the third thing down
我需要有一个地方来放置
the second one of them down.
其中的一个元素
So I have a place called t,
因此 这里有一个寄存器
which is a register just for temporary, t,
用来存放临时值T
with a button on it.
上面有一个按钮
And then I'll take the result of that,
我会使用它的结果
since I have to take that and put into b, over here,
因为我需要把这个结果送入B
we'll take the result of that and go like this,
我们会把结果像这样给送过来
and a button here.
这里同样有一个按钮
So that's the datapaths of a GCD machine.
这就是GCD机器的数据通路
Now what's the controller?
那么 控制器又是怎样的呢？
Controller's a very simple thing, too.
控制器同样很简单
The machine has a state.
机器具有状态
The way I like to visualize that is that I've got a maze.
我喜欢形象地把它们比作迷宫
And the maze has a bunch of places connected by directed arrows.
这个迷宫的各处是通过直接的箭头连接的
And what I have is a marble,
而我有一颗弹珠
which represents the state of the controller.
它代表了控制器的状态
The marble rolls around in the maze.
弹珠在迷宫中四处滚动
Of course, this analogy breaks down for energy reasons.
当然 这种类比因能量的原因而不成立
I sometimes have to pump the marble up to the top,
有时我不得不将弹珠泵到顶部
because it's going to otherwise be a perpetual motion machine.
不然它就会成为一台永动机
But not worrying about that,
但不用担心那么多
this is not a physical analogy.
这并不是一个物理比喻
This marble rolls around.
弹珠到处滚动
And every time it rolls around certain bumpers,
就像弹球机一样
like in a pinball machine,
每次当它滚动到一些缓冲器时
it pushes one of these buttons.
它就会按下这些按钮
And every so often, it comes to a place, which is a division,
它也会经常来到一个分支区域
where it has to make a choice.
它要在这里做选择
And there's a flap, which is controlled by this.
然后有一个由这个组件控制的挡板
So that's a really mechanical way of thinking about it.
所以这是一个非常机械化的思考方式
Of course, controllers not these days, are not built that way
当然 真实计算机中的控制器
in real computers.
并不是这样的
They're built with a little bit of ROM and a state register.
而是由一些ROM和状态寄存器构成
But there was a time, like the DEC PDP-6,
但曾几何时 像DEC、PDP-6这些个机器
where that's how you built the controller of a machine.
它们的控制器就是我们说的那样
There was a bit that ran around the delay line,
延迟线上有一些比特信息
and it triggered things as it went by.
它随着时间的推移而触发事件
And it would come back to the beginning and get fed round again.
然后回到开始并再次轮回
And of course, there were all sorts of great bugs you could have
当然 还有各种各样的错误
like two bits going around, two marbles.
比如两个比特的信息 -- 对应两个弹珠
And then the machine has lost its marbles.
机器也会丢失弹珠
That happens, too.
这也会发生
Oh, well.
好吧
So anyway, for this machine,
无论如何 对于这台机器
what I have to do is the following.
我想要这么来做
I'm going to start my maze here.
迷宫从这里开始
And the first thing I've got to do,
我首先要做的是
is in a notation which many of you are familiar with,
用一个你们非常熟悉的流程图记号
is b equal to zero, a test.
这是一个判断：B是否为0
And there's a possibility, either yes,
如果判断为是的话
in which case I'm done.
那我就做完了
Otherwise, if no,
否则的话
then I'm going have to roll over some bumpers.
我就不得不滚动一些缓冲器
I'm going to do it in the following order.
按照下列顺序执行
I want to, I want to do this interchange game.
我想向这样来做一个互换游戏
Now first, since I need both a and b,
首先 因为我需要A和B
but then the first-- and this is not necessary--
但首先 -- 虽然并不是必要的
I want to collect this.
我需要先把它们收集起来
This is the thing that's going to go into b.
这里的值要送入到B中
So I'm going to say,
因此 我会说
take this, which depends upon both a and b,
用A和B的值来计算这个
and put the remainder into here.
并把算得的余数放到这里
So I'm going to push this button first.
因此 我首先要按下这个按钮
Then, I'm going to transfer b to a,
然后我要把B的值送入A
push that button,
通过按这个钮来实现
and then I transfer the temporary into b,
然后我再把临时值送入B
push that button.
通过这个按钮实现
So a very sequential machine,
这是一个相当时序化的机器
it's very inefficient.
它非常的低效
But that's fine right now.
但目前来说还好
We're going to name the buttons,
我们来为按钮命名
t gets remainder.
T←R
a gets b.
A←B
And b gets t.
B←T
And then I'm going to go around here
然后我要来到这里
and it's to go back to start.
也就是回到开始的地方
And if you look, what are we seeing here?
在这里 我们看到了什么？
We're seeing the various--
我们看到各种各样的 --
what I really have is some sort of mechanical connection,
我们真正拥有的是某种机械连接
where t gets r controls this thing.
其中T←R控制了这个东西
And I have here that a gets b controls this fellow over here,
A←B控制了这个东西
and this fellow over here.
而这里的这个东西
Boy, that's absolutely pessimal,
同学们 这简直太恶劣了
the inverse of optimal.
一点也没有优化
Every line heads across every other line the way I drew it.
我画的所有线条都相互交叉
I suppose this goes here, b gets t.
我想B←T控制的是这个
Now I'd like to run this machine.
现在 我就要运行这台机器了
But before I run the machine,
但是在我运行它之前
I want to write down a description of this controller,
我想写下它的控制器的描述
just so you can see that these things,
以便使你们相信
of course, as usual, can be written down in some nice language,
这些东西可以组织成某种良好的语言
so that we don't have to always draw these diagrams.
这样我们就不必总是像这样画图
One of the problems with diagrams is that they take up a lot of space.
图示的缺陷之一 就是占用了太多空间
And for a machine this small,
对于这样的一个小型机器来说
it takes two blackboards.
它占用了两块黑板
For a machine that's the evaluator machine,
而一台求值器机器
I have trouble putting it into this room,
我就很难将它画在这间屋子里了
even though it isn't very big.
尽管它还不是非常大
So I'm going to make a little language for this
因此我要为它构造一门小型语言
that's just a description of that,
用来描述这个机器
saying define a machine we'll call GCD.
(DEFIME-MACHINE GCD
Of course, once we have something like this,
当然 一旦我们有了像这样的描述
we have a simulator for it.
我们就能够模拟该机器
And the reason why we want to build a language in this form,
我之所以想构建这种形式的语言
is because all of a sudden we can manipulate these expressions that I'm writing down.
是因为我们能够立即操纵这些表达式
And then of course I can write things I can
因此 我也就能够
algebraically manipulate these things, simulate them
代数地操作 或者模拟这些东西
all that sort of things that I might want to do,
以及各种各样我想进行的操作
perhaps transform them as a layout, who knows.
或者还可以把它们转换成布局图 谁知道呢？
Once I have a nice representation of registers,
一旦我有了寄存器的良好表示
it has certain registers,
它有一些寄存器
which we can call A, B, and T.
记作(REGISTERS A B T)
And there's a controller.
它还有控制器
Actually, a better language, which would be more explicit,
实际上 更好的做法是让它更显式一些
would be one which named every button
也就是说 为每一个按钮命名
also and said what it did.
并指明它们的操作
Like, this button
比如说这个按钮
causes the contents of T to go to the contents of B.
会让T的值送入到B中
Well I don't want to do that,
但我却不想这么做
because it's actually harder to read to do that,
因为这样会让代码难以阅读
and it takes up more space.
也会占用更多空间
So I'm going to have that in the instructions written in the controller.
所以我会把相关的指令写在控制器中
It's going to be implicit what the operations are.
这样就隐式地指明了具体的操作
They can be deduced by reading these
可以通过阅读代码推断出来
and collecting together all the different things that can be done.
并收集所有可以完成的不同事情
We look and see, see...
我们来看一看
Well, let's just look at what these things are.
我们来看下这些东西是什么吧
There's a little loop that we go around
首先是一个循环
which says branch,
先是一条分支指令
this is the representation of the little flap
这个就对应了机器中的小挡板
that decides which way you go here,
它决定了你在此处的走向
if 0, OK, fetch of B, the contents of B,
判断 -- 取B的值 并判断是否为0
and if the contents of B is 0,
如果B的值是0
then go to a place called done.
那么就跳转到一个叫DONE的地方
Now, one thing you're seeing here,
现在 你们在这里看到的是
this looks very much like a traditional computer language.
这个看起来非常像传统计算机语言
And what you're seeing here
但你们所见的是
is things like labels
一些个标签
that represent places in a sequence written down as a sequence.
它们代表着存放了一系列指令的地方
The reason why they're needed
之所以需要它们
is because over here,
是因为在这里
I've written something with loops.
我表达了“循环”的概念
But if I'm writing English text, or something like that,
但是如果我是在写英文之类的文本
it's hard to refer to a place.
就很难去引用一个位置
I don't have arrows.
我没有箭头
Arrows are represented by giving names
箭头是通过
to the places where the arrows terminate,
给箭头所指的地方命名来表示的
and then referring to them by those names.
并通过名字来引用
Now this is just an encoding.
这只是一种编码
There's nothing magical about things like that.
而不是某种魔法
Next thing we're going to do is we're going to say,
接下来我们要做的是
how do we do T gets R?
我们如何来实现T←R
Oh, that's easy enough, assign.
非常简单 用ASSIGN
We assign to T the remainder.
我们把余数赋值给T
Assign is the name of the button.
ASSIGN就是按钮的名字
That's the button-pusher.
就是按按钮的家伙
Assign to T the remainder,
把余数赋给T
and here's the representation of the operation,
这个操作是这样表示的
when we divide the fetch of A by the fetch of B.
取A、B的值 相除得到余数
And we're also going to assign to A the fetch of B,
同时 我们也要取B的值 赋给A
assign to B the result of getting the contents of T.
再取T的值赋给B
And now I have to refer to the beginning here.
现在 我需要引用这个开头
I see, why don't I call that loop like I have here?
呃 我为什么不把这里叫做LOOP呢？
OK? So that's that reference to that arrow.
这就是如何引用这个箭头
And when we're done, we're done.
当执行到DONE时 就完成了所有操作
We go to here, which is the end of the thing.
我们来到了这里 所有指令的结尾
So here's just a written representation
这段文字化描述的就是
of this fragment of machinery that we've drawn here.
我们在这里画的一小部分机器
Now the next thing I'd like to do is run this.
下面 我就要运行它
I want us to feel it running.
我想让你们感受一下它的运行
Never done this before, you got to do it once.
从来没有做过这个 你必须做一次
So let's take a particular problem.
让我们以一个具体的问题来演示
Suppose we want to compute the GCD
假设我们想要计算
of a equals 30 and b equals 42.
30和42的最大公约数
I have no idea what that is right now.
我现在不知道结果是多少
But a 30 and b is 42.
但我知道A=30而B=42
So that's how I start this thing up.
我就这么着开始
Well, what's the first thing I do?
那么 我首先要做些什么呢？
I say is B equal to 0, no.
我先判断B是否为0：否
Then assign to T the remainder of the fetch of A and the fetch of B.
然后计算A除B的余数 并赋给T
Well the remainder of 30 when divided by 42 is itself 30.
当然 30除以42的余数就是30自己
Push that button.
按下那个按钮
Now the marble has rolled to here.
现在弹珠就滚动到了这里
A gets B.
A←B
That pushes this button.
又按下了这个按钮
So 42 moves into here.
因此42来到了这里
B gets T.
B←T
Push that button.
按下了这个按钮
The 30 goes here.
30来到了这里
Let met just interchange them.
这样我就交换了它们
Now let's see, go back to the beginning.
我们再来看看 回到开始
B 0, no.
B为0么？不
T gets the remainder.
将余数赋给T
I suppose the remainder when dividing 42 by 30 is 12.
我想 42除以30的余数是12
I push that one.
按下这个钮
Next thing I do is allow the 30 to go to here,
下面 我想让30来到这里
push this one, allow the 12 to go to here.
按下这个钮 让12来到这里
OK? Go around this thing.
然后继续
Is that done?
程序执行完了么？
No.
并没有
How about-- so now I have to find out the remainder of 30 divided by 12.
现在 我需要求解30除以12的余数
And I believe that's 6.
我想答案是6
So 6 goes here on this button push.
按下这个钮 6就到了这里
Then the next thing I push is this one,
然后我又按下这个钮
which the 12 goes into here.
这就让12来到了这里
Then I push this button.
然后我又按下这个按钮
The 6 gets into here.
6就来到了这里
Is 6 equal to 0?
6等于0么？
No.
不等于
OK.
好的
So then at that point,
因此这时
the next thing to do is divide it.
接下来又要计算余数
Ooh, this has got a remainder of 0.
哦 这个的余数是0
Looks like we're almost done.
看起来我们就快完成了
Move the 6 over here next.
将6从这里挪到这里
0 over here.
0移动到这里
Is the answer 0?
0等于0么？
Yes.
是的
B is 0, therefore the answer is in A.
B的值等于0 因此答案就是A的值
The answer is 6.
因此答案就是6
And indeed that's right,
这确实是正确的答案
because if we look at the original problem,
因为如果我们回过头审视最初的问题
what we have is 30 is 2 times 3 times 5,
我们知道30=2×3×5
and 42 is 2 times 3 times 7.
42=2×3×7
So the greatest common divisor is 2 times 3,
因此最大公约数就是2×3
which is 6.
也就是6
Now normally, we write one other little line here,
我们通常在这里画另外一条线
just to make it a little bit clearer,
为了使它更清晰一点
which is that we leave in a connection saying
在这两者之间建立了联系
that this light is the guy that that flap looks at.
小挡板需要根据这个指示灯来工作
Of course, any real machine has a lot more
当然 跟我给你们展示的东西相比
complicated things in it than what I've just shown you.
真实计算机的组件更加复杂
Let's look for a second at the first still store.
让我们来看看第一张幻灯片
Wow.
哇
Well you see, for example, one thing we might want to do
我们看到 我们想要做的就是
is worry about the operations that are of IO form.
IO形式的操作
And we may have to collect something from the outside.
我们需要从外部搜集一些东西
So a state machine that we might have,
因此 对我们的状态机器来说
the controller may have to,
它们的控制器
may have to, for example, get a value from something
可能会从某处取得某值
and put register a to load it up.
将它们放入寄存器并从中读取
I have to master load up register b with another value.
我还可以把另外的值加载到寄存器B中
And then later, when I'm done,
稍后 当执行完毕后
I might want to print the answer out.
我想要输出结果
And of course, that might be either simple or complicated.
当然 答案或简单或复杂
I'm writing, assuming print is very simple,
我写代码的时候 总假设PRINT很简单
and read is very simple.
READ也很简单
But in fact, in the real world,
但实际上 在真实世界中
those are very complicated operations,
这些都是非常复杂的操作
fairly, usually much, much larger and more complicated
跟你尝试求解的问题相比
than the thing you're doing as your problem you're trying to solve.
它们通常更加庞大而复杂
On the other hand, I can remember a time when,
另一方面 我犹记得
I remember using IBM 7090 computer of sorts,
使用IBM 7090一类的计算机的时候
where things like read and write of a single object,
它的READ和WRITE只能操作单个对象
a single number, a number,
也就是一个数字
is a primitive operation of the IO controller.
这就是一个基本的IO操作
OK? And so we have that kind of thing in there.
我们这里有同样的操作
And in such a machine,
在这样的一台机器中
well, what are we really doing?
我们实际上在做什么？
We're just saying that there's a source over here called "read"
我们看到 这个叫做“READ”的组件是数据源头
which is an operation which always has a value.
这个操作总是返回一个值
We have to think about this as always having a value
我们可以把它看做 总是返回一个值
which can be gated into either register a or b.
它可以赋给寄存器A或B
And print is some sort of thing
而PRINT这个过程呢
which when you gate it appropriately,
当你正确连接它的时候
when you push the button on it,
当你按下上面的按钮
will cause a print of the value that's currently in register a.
就会打印出当前寄存器A中的值
Nothing very exciting.
这非常普通
So that's one sort of thing you might want to have.
这是我们想要的一种功能
But these are also other things that are a little bit worrisome.
但这里还有些其它事情需要我们担忧
Like I've used here some complicated mechanisms.
比如说 这里我使用了一些复杂的机制
What you see here is remainder.
我们这里有REMAINDER组件
What is that?
这是个什么东西呢？
That may not be so obvious how to compute.
求取余数的计算过程并不是那么“显然”
It may be something which when you open it up,
如果我们把这个组件给拆开
you get a whole machine.
就会得到一整台机器
OK? In fact, that's true.
事实就是这样的
For example, if I write down the program for remainder,
举例来说 如果要编程实现REMAINDER
the simplest program for it is by repeated subtraction.
最简单的算法就是 不断地做减法
Because of course, division can be done
这是因为 除法可以通过
by repeated subtraction of numbers, of integers.
对整数不断做减法来实现
So the remainder of N divided by D
N除以D的余数不外乎就是
is nothing more than if N is less than D,
如果N小于D的话
then the result is N.
答案就是N
Otherwise, it's the remainder
否则的话就是
when we subtract D from N with respect to D,
N先减去D
when divided by D.
再除以D的余数
Gee, this looks just like the GCD program.
天啊 这个看起来就像是GCD程序
Of course, it's not a very nice way to do remainders.
当然 这个不是求余数的最优算法
You'd really want to use something like
在实际中 你应该使用那些
binary notation and shift and things like that in a practical computer.
二进制运算、移位运算等操作
But the point of that is
但关键点就是
that if I open this thing up,
如果我把这些组件打开
I might find inside of it a computer.
我可能会发现其中有一台计算机
Oh, we know how to do that.
现在我们就知道它的原理了
We just made one.
因为我们就造过一台
And it could be another thing just like this.
这些个机器都大同小异
On the other hand,
另外一方面
we might want to make a more efficient
我们可能想要构建一台更高效
or better-structured machine,
组织更精良的机器
or maybe make use of some of the registers more than once,
比如说 多次利用其中的寄存器
or some horrible mess like that that hardware designers like to do,
或者是硬件设计者能想到的其它可怕混乱
and for very good reasons.
等等原因
So for example, here's a machine that you see,
比如说 你们所见的这台机器
which you're not supposed to be able to read.
不是让你们去细读它的结构的
It's a little bit complicated. OK?
它有些复杂 对吧？
But what it is is the integration of
但它实际上是
remainder into the GCD machine.
整合了REMAINDER的GCD机器
And it takes, in fact, no more registers.
并且实际上 它没有多余的寄存器
There are three registers in the datapaths. OK?
数据通路上有三个寄存器
But now there's a subtractor.
但现在 这里有个减法器
There are two things that are tested.
又有两个东西被测试
Is b equal to 0,
B等于0么？
or is t less than b?
T小于B么？
And then the controller, which you see over here,
而至于这一块的控制器
is not much more complicated.
并不会更加复杂
But it has two loops in it,
它有两个循环
one of which is the main one for doing the GCD,
最主要的循环是计算GCD的
and one of which is the subtraction loop
而另一条是减法循环
for doing the remainder sub-operation.
是用来计算余数的子操作
And there are ways, of course, of,
当然 还有一种思考方式
if you think about it, taking the remainder program.
就是把求余数程序
If I take remainder, as you see over there
如果我把那边的REMAINDER机器
as a lambda expression,
当作LAMBDA表达式
substitute it in for remainder over here in the GCD program,
代换到GCD程序的REMAINDER中
OK, then do some simplification
然后再做一些化简
by substituting a and b for remainder in there,
代换其中的A和B
then I can unwind this loop.
那么 我就可以展开这个循环
And I can get this piece of machinery
那么我就可以通过
by basically, a little bit of simplification
LAMBDA表达式的基本代数化简
algebraic simplification on the lambda expressions.
来得到这台机器
So I suppose you've seen your first very simple machines now.
我想 你们已经见识了一个非常简单的机器了
Are there any questions?
有什么疑问么？
Good.
很好
This looks easy, doesn't it?
看起来很容易 难道不是吗？
Thank you. I suppose, take a break.
好吧 休息一下 谢谢大家
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
[音乐]
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
讲师：哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
寄存机器
PROFESSOR: Well, let's see.
教授：好吧
Now you know how to make an iterative procedure,
现在 你们已经知道如何去把迭代过程
or a procedure that yields an iterative process,
或者是产生迭代计算的过程
turn into a machine.
变成一台机器
I suppose the next thing we want to do is worry about things
我想 接下来我们就应该考虑
that reveal recursive processes.
如何来处理递归过程了
So let's play with a simple factorial procedure.
我们先从一个简单的阶乘过程开始
We define factorial of N to be
(DEFINE (FACT N)
if n is 1, the result is 1,
如果N=1 那么结果就是1
using 1 right now to decrease the amount of work I have to do to simulate it,
为了减少模拟它的工作量 我就使用1
else it's times N factorial N minus 1.
否则结果就是(* N (FACT (- N 1)))
And what's different with this program, as you know,
正如你们所知 这个程序的不同之处在于
is that after I've computed factorial of N minus 1 here,
这里 我在计算(FACT (- N 1))之后
I have to do something to the result.
我要对结果做一些运算
I have to multiply it by N.
我要将它与N相乘
So the only way I can visualize what this machine is doing,
将这台机器可视化的唯一途径就是
because of the fact--
首先 由于--
think of it this way,
请你们这么来想
that I have a machine out here
这里 我有一台机器
which somehow needs a factorial machine in order to compute its answer.
而这台机器又需要某个阶乘机器来计算结果
But this machine, the outer machine,
但外面的这台机器
has to exist before and after
又需要在调用内部阶乘机器
the factorial machine, which is inside.
的前后都要存在
Whereas in the iterative case,
然而在迭代情况中
the outer machine doesn't need to exist
外面的机器不需要
after the inner machine is running,
在内部机器运行后保持存在
because you never need to go back
这是因为你不需要回到
to the outer machine to do anything.
外部机器来进行其它操作
So here we have a problem
因此 我们这里的问题是
where we have a machine
我们的机器内部
which has the same machine inside of it,
有一个同样的机器
an infinitely large machine.
一台无穷大的机器
And it's got other things inside of it, like a multiplier,
这里面也有其它的东西 比如乘法器
which takes some inputs,
它接收输入
and there's a minus 1 box,
这是-1操作
and things like that.
等等
You know, You can imagine that's what it looks like.
你们可以想象 -- 它就是这个样子的
But the important thing is that here I have
但重要之处就在于
something that happens before and after,
内部机器执行之前与执行之后
in the outer machine, the execution of the inner machine.
外部机器中都进行了一些运算
So this machine has to have a life.
因此这台机器必须有“生命”
It has to exist on both times sides of this machine.
外部机器需要在内部机器的两个时间点保持存在
So somehow, I have to have a place to store
因此 我就需要有一个地方来保存
the things that this thing needs to run.
维持外部机器运转的数据
Infinite objects don't exist in the real world.
现实世界中不存在无穷的对象
What we have to do is arrange an illusion
我们要做的就是营造一种假象
that we have an infinite object,
一种无穷对象的假象
we have an infinite amount of hardware somewhere.
我们在某处有无穷的硬件资源
Now of course, illusion's all that really matters.
现在 这个假象非常重要
If we can arrange
如果我们能保证
that every time you look at some infinite object,
每次当你查看某个无穷对象时
the part of it that you look at is there,
你所要观察的那部分存在
then it's as infinite as you need it to be.
那么就不需要实际上的“无穷”
And of course, one of the things we might want to do,
当然 这里面我们想做的就是
just look at this thing over here,
来看下这里的东西
is the organization that we've had so far
这是我们目前为止的结构
organization that we've had so far
这些结构呢
involves having a part of the machine,
是机器的几大部分
which is the controller,
比如控制器
which sits right over here,
它在这里
which is perfectly finite and very simple.
它相当简单 并且是有穷的
We have some datapaths,
我们还有数据通路
which consist of registers and operators.
它由寄存器和运算器组成
And what I propose to do here is decompose
现在我提议
the machine into two parts,
把机器分成两部分
such that there is a part which is fundamentally finite,
这样 其中一部分全部是有穷的
and some part where a certain amount of infinite stuff can be kept.
而另一部分 可以保存无穷数据中的一部分
On the other hand this is very simple
换句话说 这部分也非常简单
and really isn't infinite, but it's just very large.
但并非无穷 只是非常大而已
But it's so simple
但它非常简单
that it could be cheaply reproduced in such large amounts,
以至于能够廉价地大量生产
we call it memory,
它就是内存
OK? that we can make a structure called a stack out of it
我们可以利用它来构造栈结构
which will allow us to, in fact,
事实上 这就使得我们
simulate the existence of an infinite machine
能够模拟无穷机器的存在
which is made out of a recursive nest of many machines.
也就是那些递归嵌套的机器
And the way it's going to work is that
而它的原理则是
we're going to store in this place called the stack
我们要在栈上存放必要的信息
the information required after the inner machine runs
用于内部机器执行完毕后
to resume the operation of the outer machine.
继续外部机器的操作
So it will remember
因此它会记住
the important things about the life of the outer machine
关于外部机器生命期的重要数据
that will be needed for this computation.
这些是进行计算所必需的
Since, of course,
当然
these machines are nested in a recursive manner,
由于这些机器是通过递归的方式嵌套的
then in fact the stack will only be accessed in a manner
因此 栈的存取方式也会是
which is the last thing that goes in is the first thing that comes out.
也会是后进先出的
So we'll only need to access
因此我们只需要存取
some little part of this stack memory.
这个栈内存的一小部分
OK, well, let's do it.
好吧 让我们来试一试
I'm going to build you a datapath now,
我已经给你们画好了数据通路
and I'm going to write the controller.
现在该布置控制器了
And then we're going to execute this to see how you do it.
然后我们来运行一下 观察实际工作原理
So the factorial machine isn't so bad.
还好阶乘机器不是特别的复杂
It's going to have a register called the value,
它有一个VAL寄存器
where the answer is going to be stored,
这是用来存储答案的
and a registered called N,
还有一个寄存器N
which is where the number I'm taking factorial will be stored, factorial of.
它里面存储的是要计算阶乘的数
And it will be necessary in some instances
为了满足某些情况
to connect VAL to N.
我们要连接VAL和N
In fact, one nice case of this is if I just said over here,
事实上 如果我在这里返回N
N, because that would be right for N equal 1N.
也是正确的 因为这时N就等于1
And I could just move the answer over there if that's important.
这样的话 我就可以把结果移动过去
I'm not worried about that right now.
但我现在不考虑这个问题
And there are things I have to be able to do.
我还需要做一些事情
Like I have to be able to, as we see here,
就像我们在这里看到的 我们还需要
multiply N by something in VAL,
用VAL的值乘以N
because VAL is the result of computing factorial.
因为VAL是计算阶乘的结果
And I have to put the result back into VAL.
我需要把算得的结果送回VAL
So here we can see
所以这里我们看到
that the result of computing a factorial
N的阶乘就是
is N times the result of computing a factorial.
N乘以某个阶乘
VAL will be the representation of the answer of the inner factorial.
而VAL就代表了内部阶乘的结果
And so I'm going to have to have a multiplier here,
因此 在这里我需要有一个乘法器
which is going to sample the value of N and the value of VAL
它的参数有：N以及VAL
OK? and put the result back into VAL like that.
并且 像这样把计算结果送回VAL
I'm also going to have to be able to see if N is 1.
我也需要知道N是否为1
So I need a light bulb.
因此我需要一个指示灯
And I suppose the other thing I'm going to need to have
另外 我想我还需要
is a way of decrementing N.
一个组件来减小N
So I'm going to have a decrementer,
所以这里有一个递减器
which takes N and is going to put back the result into N.
它接收参数N 将结果送回N
That's pretty much what I need in my machine.
这基本上就是我的机器所需要的东西了
Now, there's a little bit else I need.
然而 我还需要一些个东西
It's a little bit more complicated,
一个稍微复杂一点的东西
because I'm also going to need a way to store,
因为我需要有一种方式能够存储
to save away, the things that are going to be needed
必要的一些信息
for resuming the computation of a factorial
以便计算完子阶乘后
after I've done a sub-factorial.
恢复原始阶乘的计算
What's that?
需要哪些信息呢?
One thing I need is N.
首先就是N
So I'm going to build here a thing called a stack.
因此 我要在这里构造一个栈
The stack is
所谓的栈就是
a bunch of stuff that I'm going to write in sequentially.
一大堆连续的空间
I don't know how long it is.
我不知道它到底有多深
The longer it is, the better my illusion of infinity.
栈越深 无穷的假象营造得就越好
And I'm going to have to have a way of getting stuff
我还需要有一种方法 能够把
out of N and into the stack
N中的值放入栈中
and vice versa.
反过来也是
So I'm going to need a connection like this,
因此我需要一条像这样的连接
which is two-way,
它是双向的
whereby I can save the value of N
通过它 我就可以在某个时间
and then restore it some other time through that connection.
把N的值存储起来
This is the stack.
这就是栈
I also need a way of remembering
我还需要一种方法来记住
where I was in the computation of factorial in the outer program.
我现在计算到外部程序的哪个地方了
Now in the case of this machine,
现在 对于这台机器来说
it isn't very much a problem.
这并不是什么问题
Factorial always returns,
FACT总是返回在
has to go back to the place where we multiply by N,
一个跟N相乘的地方
except for the last time,
除了最后的一次
when it has to return to whatever needs the factorial
它返回到需要FACT最终答案的地方
or go to done or stop.
或者是'DONE、'STOP之类的
However, in general,
然而 通常来说
I'm going to have to remember where I have been,
我需要记住我去过哪些地方
because I might have computed factorial from somewhere else.
因为 我可能从其它地方调用FACT
I have to go back to that place and continue there.
我需要返回到那个地方 并从那里继续
So I'm going to have to have some way of taking the place
因此 我需要有一种方法能够
where the marble is in the finite state controller,
记住有穷状态控制器中弹珠的位置
the state of the controller,
也就是控制器的状态
and storing that in the stack as well.
并将它存储在栈中
And I'm going to have to have ways of restoring that
我也需要有一种方法
back to the state of the-- the marble.
能够恢复弹珠的状态
So I have to have something that moves the marble to the right place.
因此 我需要有一种将弹珠归位的能力
Well, we're going to have a place which is the marble now.
现在 我们有一个地方用于存储弹珠
And it's called the continue register,
它被称作“继续”寄存器
called continue,
记作CONTINUE
which is the place to put the marble
下一次调用(GOTO CONTINUE)时
next time I go to continue.
弹珠就会去向这个地方
That's what that's for.
它就是用来干这个的
And so there's got to be some path from that into the controller.
因此 它和控制器之间应该有一条通路
I also have to have some way of saving that on the stack.
我也能够将它存储在栈上
And I have to have some way of setting that up to have various constants,
我也能够把它设置成各种常量
a certain fixed number of constants.
某一些常量
And that's very easy to arrange.
这非常容易实现
So let's have some constants here.
我们现在这里设一些常量
We'll call this one after-fact.
我们把这个记作AFTER-FACT
And that's a constant
这个常量
which will get into the continue register,
会送入CONTINUE寄存器
and also another one called fact-done.
另外一个寄存器是FACT-DONE
So this is the machine I want to build.
这就是我想要构建的机器
That's its datapaths, at least.
至少是数据通路部分
And it mixes a little with the controller here,
这里还混合了一些控制器
because of the fact that I have to remember where I was
这是因为我需要记住我当前的位置
and restore myself to that place.
并将我恢复到该位置
But let's write the program now which represents the controller.
现在 让我们来编写控制器对应的程序
I'm not going to write the define machine thing and the register list,
我就把DEFINE-MACHINE和寄存器列表给省略了
because that's not very interesting.
因为它们无关紧要
I'm just going to write down the sequence of instructions
我就直接写那些跟控制器有关的
that constitute the controller.
指令序列
So we have assign, to set up, continue to done.
首先是(ASSIGN CONTINUE DONE)
We have a loop
然后是一个循环
which says branch if equal 1 fetch N,
先判断 如果1=N 那么就跳转
if N is 1, then go to the base step of the induction,
那么就进入归纳的基本步骤
the simple case.
也就是最简单的情况
Otherwise,
否则的话
I have to remember the things that are necessary
我就要记住那些
to perform a sub-factorial.
计算子阶乘所必须的信息
I'm going to go over here, and I have to perform a sub-factorial.
我需要来带这里 以便计算子阶乘
So I have to remember what's needed to do that
所以我需要记住 完成它需要些什么
remember what's needed after I will be done with that.
需要记住我计算完之后需要哪些东西
See, I'm about to do something terrible.
看到了吗 我要做些糟糕的事儿
I'm about to change the value of N.
我要去修改N的值
But this guy has to know the old value of N.
但是它又需要记住N的旧值
But in order to make the sub-factorial work,
但是为了计算子阶乘
I have to change the value of N.
我又需要修改N的值
So I have to remember the old value.
因此 我就得记住N的旧值
And I also have to remember where I've been.
我也需要记住我的位置
So I save up continue.
因此 我保存CONTINUE的值
And this is an instruction that says, put something in the stack.
这条指令 就是用来将数据入栈的
Save the contents of the continuation register,
将CONTINUE寄存器的值保存起来
which in this case is done,
在本例中也就是DONE
because later I'm going to change that, too,
因为稍后我也会修改它
because I need to go back to after-fact, as well.
因为我也需要回到AFTER-FACT
We'll see that.
我们来看看
We save N, because I'm going to need that for later.
我们需要存储N 因为稍后会用到
Assign to N the decrement of fetch N.
(ASSIGN N (-1+ (FETCH N)))
Assign continue,
(ASSIGN CONTINUE ...
we're going to look at this now,
我看一下 --
to after, we'll call it.
AFT)
That's a good name for this,
这个名字很好
a little bit easier and shorter, and fits in here.
因为它短小精炼 很适合用在这里
Now look what I'm doing here.
现在 来看看我怎么做
I'm saying, if the answer is 1,
我说 如果ANSWER是1的话
OK, I'm done.
那程序就结束了
I'm going to have to just get the answer.
我只需要取得这个答案
Otherwise, I'm going to save the continuation, save N,
否则我就要保存当前的继续以及N的值
make N one less than N,
然后让N减1
remember I'm going to come back to someplace else,
注意 我先要跳转到某处
and go back and start doing another factorial.
然后来到这里 计算另外的阶乘
OK? However, I've got a different machine in me now.
然而 这之中又有了另外的机器
N is 1, and continue is something else.
其中N=1 CONTINUE是其它值
N is N minus 1.
N=N-1
Now after I'm done with that,
再我完成这个之后
I can go there.
我会来到这里
I will restore the old value of N,
我会恢复N的旧值
which is the opposite of this save over here.
也就是这里SAVE的逆运算
I will restore the continuation.
然后恢复CONTINUE
I will then go to here.
然后我又会来到这里
I will assign to the VAL register
(ASSIGN VAL
the product of N and fetch VAL.
(* (FETCH N) (FETCH VAL)))
VAL fetch product assign.
（闭合括号中）
And then I will be done.
这样操作就完成了
I will have my answer to the sub-factorial in VAL.
子阶乘的结果就存储在了VAL中
At that point,
这个时候
I'm going to return
我就要返回到
by going to the place where the continuation is pointing.
CONTINUE所指向的地方
That says, go to fetch continue.
也就是(GOTO (FETCH CONTINUE))
And then I have finally a base step,
最后就是基本情况的那步
which is the immediate answer.
也就是一个立即值
Assign to VAL fetch N,
(ASSIGN VAL (FETCH N))
and go to fetch continue.
(GOTO (FETCH CONTINUE))
And then I'm done.
这样我就完成了
Now let's see how this executes on a very simple case,
现在 我们用一个非常简单的例子来运行一下
because then we'll see
因为这样我们就将看到
the use of this stack to do the job we need.
栈是如何帮助我们完成计算的
This is statically what it's doing,
这是计算的静态描述
but we have look dynamically at this.
我们需要动态地观察它
So let's see.
因此 让我们来看看
First thing we do is continue gets done.
首先我们要把CONTINUE设置为DONE
The way that happened is I pushed this.
这是我通过按下这个钮来实现的
Let's call that done the way I have it.
我们还是把它记作DONE吧
I push that button.
我按下这个按钮
Done goes into there.
DONE就进到了这里
Now I also have to set this thing up to have an initial value.
现在 我还要为这些东西设置初始值
Let's consider a factorial of three,
让我们考虑3的阶乘
a simple case.
这个例子非常简单
And we're going to start out with our stack growing over here.
我们的栈从这里开始增长
Stacks have their own little internal state
栈有它们自己的内部状态
saying where they are,
用来标识栈顶位置
where the next place I'm going to write is.
也就是下一个可写位置
So now we say, is N 1?
现在我们问 N=1么？
The answer is no.
当然不等于
So now I'm going to save continue, bang.
因此现在我要保存CONTINUE
Now that done goes in here.
现在 DONE就来到了这里
And this moves to here,
然后 这个指针移动到了这里
the next place I'm going to write.
下次我要把数据写到这里
Save N 3.
保存N的值--也就是3
OK?
对吧？
Assign to N the decrement of N.
N←N-1
That means I've pushed this button.
也就是说 我得按下这个钮
This becomes 2.
这就变成了2
OK? Assign to continue aft.
COUNTINUE←AFT
So I've pushed that button.
因此我要按下这个钮
Aft goes in here.
AFT就进入了这里
OK, now go to loop, bang, so up to here.
然后 跳转到LOOP 我们就来到了这里
Is N 1? No
N=1么？当然不
So I have to save continue.
因此我又要保存CONTINUE
What's continue?
CONTINUE的值是什么呢？
Continue is aft.
目前是AFT
Push this button.
按下这个按钮
So this moves to here.
这个指针移动到了这里
I have to save N.
我还要保存N
N is over here. I got to 2.
N在那里 它的值是2
Push that button.
按下这个按钮
So a 2 gets written there.
2就进入了这里
And then this thing moves down here.
然后这个指针移动到了这里
OK, save N. Assign N to the decrement of N.
保存N之后 又赋N←N-1
This becomes a 1.
它就变成了1
Assign continue to aft.
CONTINUE←AFT
A-F-T gets written there again.
AFT又进入了这里
Go to loop.
然后又跳转到LOOP
Is N equal to 1?
N等于1么？
Oh, yes, the answer is 1.
是的 那么答案就是1
OK, go to base step.
跳转到BASE那一步
Assign to VAL fetch of N.
(ASSIGN VAL (FETCH N))
Bang, 1 gets put in there. OK?
按下这个 1就进入到了这里
Go to fetch continue.
(GOTO (FETCH CONTINUE))
So we look in continue.
来看下CONTINUE寄存器
Basically, I'm pushing a button over here that goes to the controller.
基本上来说 我按下这里的按钮 进入到控制器
The continue becomes aft,
CONTINUE寄存器就变成了AFT
and all of a sudden, the program's running here.
这样一下子 程序就运行到了这里
I now have to restore the outer version of factorial.
现在 我就需要恢复外部的阶乘了
So we go here.
因此我们来到这里
We say, restore N.
我们先要恢复N
So restore N means take the contents that's here.
这就意味着 我们要使用这里的内容
Push this button, and it goes into here, 2,
按下这个按钮 2就会来到这里
and the pointer moves up.
然后指针会向上移动
Restore continue, pretty easy.
恢复CONTINUE寄存器也非常简单
Go push this button.
来按下这个按钮
And then aft gets written in here again.
然后 AFT又一次进入到这里
That means this thing moves up.
同时 这个指针也要上移
I've gotten rid of something else on my stack.
这样就避开了栈上的其它东西
Right, then I go to here,
然后我来到这里
which says, assign to VAL the product of N and VAL.
也就是(ASSIGN VAL (* N VAL))
So I push this button over here, bang.
然后我按下这个按钮
2 times 1 gives me a 2,
2乘以1等于2
get written there.
我写到这里
OK? Go to fetch continue.
然后是(GOTO (FETCH CONTINUE))
Continue is aft. I go to aft.
CONTINUE现在是AFT 我跳转到AFT
OK? Aft says restore N.
AFT首先要恢复N
Do your restore N,
恢复N指的是
means I take the value over here, which is 3,
我把这里的值 也就是3
push this up to here,
按下这里的按钮
and move it into here, N.
然后把它放到这里 N
Now it's pushing that button.
然后 我们按下这个钮
The next thing I do is restore continue.
接下来我就要恢复CONTINUE
Continue is now going to become done.
CONTINUE寄存器现在成为了DONE
So this moves up here when I push this button.
当我按下这个钮后 指针就移动到了这里
Done may or may be there anymore,
DONE可能从此之后不在这里了
I'm not interested, but it certainly is here.
对此我并不感兴趣 但它现在一定在这里
Next thing I do is assign to VAL
下一步 我将要把VAL赋值为
the product of the fetch of N and the fetch of VAL.
N乘以VAL的值
That's pushing this button over here, bang.
按下这里的按钮就可以实现
2 times 3 is 6.
2乘以3等于6
So I get a 6 over here.
所以这里我就得到了6
OK? And go to fetch continue,
下一步是(GOTO (FETCH CONTINUE))
whoops, I go to done, and I'm done.
哦 跳转到DONE 这样我就完成了
And my answer is 6,
最后的答案是6
as you can see in the VAL register.
你们可以在VAL寄存器中看到
And in fact,
事实上
the stack is in the state it originally was in.
栈又回到了它初始的状态
Now there's a bit of discipline in using these things like stacks
在使用像栈这样的东西中 有一些原则
that we have to be careful of.
我们需要注意
And we'll see that in the next segment.
我们会在下一小节中介绍
But first I want to ask if there are any questions for this.
但首先 对于这一小节所讲的内容
Are there any questions?
有什么问题么？
Yes, Ron.
Ron 请讲
AUDIENCE: What happens when you roll off the end of the stack with--
学生：当你越过了栈的顶端会怎样--
PROFESSOR: What do you mean, roll off of?
教授：你所谓的“越过”是指什么？
AUDIENCE: Well, the largest number-- a larger starting point of N
学生：如果我们的N是一个很大的数
requires more memory, correct?
就需要更多的内存 对吧？
PROFESSOR: Oh, yes.
教授：是的
Well, I need to have a long enough stack.
这样 我就需要一个足够大的栈
You say, what if I violate my illusion?
你想问 如果破坏了无穷存储的假象会发生什么？
AUDIENCE: Yes.
学生：是的
PROFESSOR: Well, then the magic doesn't work. OK?
教授：那么 这些魔法就不再起效了
The truth of the matter is that every machine is finite.
真相就是 任何机器都是有穷的
And for a procedure like this,
而对于像这样的过程
there's a limit to the number of sub-factorials I could have.
我只能进行有限数量的子阶乘计算
Remember when we were doing the y-operator a while ago,
想一想 我们之前讲解的Y组合子
we pointed out that there was a sequence of exponentiation procedures,
我们指出 存在一系列的指数过程
each of which was a little better than the previous one.
其中每一个都要比前一个更精准
Well, we're now seeing how we implement that mathematical idea.
现在 我们看到了如何实现这个数学理念
The limiting process
这个取极限的过程
is only so good as as far as you take the limit.
只有当你取到极限时才足够精准
If you think about it, what am I using here?
如果你仔细想想 我这里用了什么
I'm using about two chunks, pieces of memory
对于这个过程的每一次递归
for iteration for every recursion of this process.
我用了大概两块内存
If we try to compute factorial of 10,000,
如果我们尝试计算10000的阶乘
that's not a lot of memory.
这并不会花掉很多内存
On the other hand, it's an awful big number.
虽然这是一个很大的数
So the question is, is that a valuable thing in this case.
因此 实际的问题就是值不值得
But it really turns out not to be a terrible limit,
但这并不是这种实现的局限
because memory is el cheapo,
因为内存非常低廉
and people are pretty expensive.
但人力资源却相当昂贵
OK, thank you, let's take a break.
好吧 我们先休息一下 谢谢大家
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
[音乐]
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
讲师：哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
寄存机器
PROFESSOR: Well, let's see.
教授：我们讲解了
What I've shown you now is how to do a simple iterative process
如果进行简单的迭代计算
and a simple recursive process.
以及简单的递归计算
I just want to summarize the design of simple machines
我只想通过向你们展示一些针对特定应用的
for specific applications
更加复杂的设计
by showing you a little bit more complicated design,
来总结简单机器的设计
that of a thing that does doubly recursive Fibonacci,
也就是同时递归地调用两个斐波那契函数
because it will indicate to us, and we'll understand,
因为它会向我们表明 并且我们会理解
a bit about the conventions required
一些关于栈正常工作
for making stacks operate correctly.
所需要遵守的约定
So let's see.
现在 让我们来看看
I'm just going to write down, first of all,
先让我在黑板上写下
the program I'm going to translate.
将要翻译的程序
I need a Fibonacci procedure,
这是一个斐波那契过程
it's very simple, which says, if
它非常的简单
N is less than 2, the result is N,
如果N小于2 那么结果就是N
otherwise it's the sum of Fib of N minus 1
否则就是(FIB (- N 1))加上
and Fib of N minus 2.
(FIB (- N 2))
That's the plan I have here.
这就是我的计划
And we're just going to write down the controller for such a machine.
现在 我们要来写下这台机器的控制器
We're going to assume that there are registers, N,
首先 我们假设有一个寄存器N
which holds the number we're taking Fibonacci of,
里面存放的是斐波那契函数的自变量
VAL, which is where the answer is going to get put,
而计算结果会存放在VAL寄存器中
and continue, which is the thing that's linked to the controller,
CONTINUE寄存器会和控制器相连
like before.
就跟之前一样
But I'm not going to draw another physical datapath,
但我不会再去画数据通路了
because it's pretty much the same as the last one you've seen.
因为它和之前的那个差不多
And of course, one of the most amazing things about computation
当然 关于计算的最神奇的事情之一
is that after a while,
就是一段时间后
you build up a little more features and a few more features,
你构建了一个又一个的小功能
and all of the sudden, you've got everything you need.
你就一下子拥有了需要的一切
So it's remarkable that it just gets there so fast.
这种效率是非常了不起的
I don't need much more to make a universal computer.
构造制作一台通用计算机不需要太多的东西
But in any case, let's look at the controller for the Fibonacci thing.
总之 我们来看看斐波那契机器的控制器
First thing I want to do is
我首先要做的是
start the thing up by assign to continue
通过为CONTINUE寄存器赋值
a place called done, called Fib-done here.
赋FIB-DONE来启动计算
So that means that somewhere over here,
这就意味着在这里
I'm going to have a label, Fib-done,
我需要有一个标签 FIB-DONE
which is the place where I go
当我来到这个地方后
when I want the machine to stop.
机器就停止了
That's what that is.
这就是这个标签的作用
And I'm going to make up a loop.
然后我要创建一个循环
It's a place I'm going to go to in order to start up computing a Fib.
我要来到这里来启动FIB的计算
Whatever is in N at this point,
无论这时 N等于多少
Fibonacci will be computed of,
斐波那契函数都会被计算
and we will return to the place specified by continue.
然后会返回到由CONTINUE寄存器指向的地方
So what you're going to see here at this place,
因此你们将在这里看到
what I want here is the contract
我想要在做一个约定
that says, I'm going to write this with a comment syntax,
我用注释的形式来说明这个约定
the contract is N contains arg, the argument.
也就是N中存储的是参数
Continue is the recipient.
而CONTINUE存储的是接收者
And that's where it is.
这个约定就是这样的
At this point, if I ever go to this place,
因此每当我来到这里
I'm expecting this to be true,
我希望这个约定是成立的
the argument for computing the Fibonacci.
这些计算斐波那契函数所需要的参数
Now the next thing I want to do is to branch.
接下来我想做的是分支
And if N is less than 2--
如果N小于2
by the way, I'm using what looks like Lisp syntax.
随便说一下 我使用的语法看起来像Lisp
This is not Lisp.
但它并不是Lisp
This does not run.
它们运行不起来
What I'm writing here does not run as a simple Lisp program.
我在这里写的并不是一个简单的Lisp程序
This is a representation of another language.
这是另一门语言的表示形式
The reason I'm using the syntax of parentheses and so on
我之所以使用这种满是括号的语法
is because I tend to use a Lisp system
是因为我刚好使用Lisp系统
to write an interpreter for this
来为这门语言编写解释器
which allows me to simulate
这就使得我们能够模拟
the machine I'm trying to build.
我想要构建的机器
I don't want to confuse this to think that this is Lisp code.
我不想让你们感到困惑 认为这是Lisp代码
It's just I'm using a lot of the pieces of Lisp.
只是我用了很多Lisp组件
I'm embedding a language in Lisp,
我在Lisp中嵌入了一门语言
using Lisp as pieces
把Lisp当作组件
to make my process of making my simulator easy.
这样就能让我的模拟工作变得简单
So I'm inheriting from Lisp all of its properties.
我从Lisp中继承了这些属性
Fetch of N 2,
(FETCH N) 2)
I want to go to a place called immediate answer.
成立的话 我想要跳转到IMMEDIATE-ANSWER这个地方
It's the base step.
这是基本步骤
Now, that's somewhere over here,
它对应在这里
just above done.
也就是在FIB-DONE的上方
And we'll see it later.
我们稍后就会看到
Now, in the general case,
现在 对于一般情况来说
which is the part I'm going to write down now,
也就是我现在要写的
let's just do it.
是这样的
Well, first of all, I'm going to have to call Fibonacci twice.
首先呢 我需要调用斐波那契函数两次
In each case-- well, in one case at least,
在每一次中 -- 至少在其中一次
I'm going to have to know what to do
我得需要知道该怎么做
to come back and do the next one.
才能回过头来进行另外一个计算
I have to remember,
我需要记住
have I done the first Fib,
我计算完第一个FIB了么？
or have I done the second one?
或者第二个也计算完了？
Do I have to come back to the place where I do the second Fib,
我是该返回到计算第二个FIB的地方
or do I have to come back to the place where I do the add?
还是回到执行ADD的地方
In both cases I going to need, I don't
无论哪种情况 我都需要--
In the first case, over the first Fibonacci,
在第一个计算第一个FIB时
I'm going to need the value of N for computing for the second one.
我需要保存N的值 来计算第二个FIB
So I have to store some of these things up.
因此我要把这些东西保存起来
So first I'm going to save continue.
首先要保存CONTINUE
That's who needs the answer.
也就是答案的接收者
And the reason I'm doing that
我之所以要这么做
is because I'm about to assign continue
是因为我现在要把CONTINUE赋值为
to the place which is the place I want to go to after.
我待会儿想要返回的地方
Let's call it Fib-N-minus-1,
我们把它叫做AFTER-FIB-N-1
big long name, classic Lisp name.
这个长名字 非常具有Lisp的命名特点
Because I'm going to compute the first Fib of N minus 1,
这是因为我先要计算第一个(FIB (- N 1))
and then after that,
计算完成之后
I want to come back and do something else.
我想要回过头来做些其它事
That's the place I want to go to after I've done
而AFTER-FIB-N-1这个地方
the first Fibonacci calculation.
就是我计算完第一个FIB后应该返回的地方
And I want to do a save of N,
接下来我要保存N
because I'm going to need it later, after that.
因为我稍后需要用到它
Now I'm going to, at this point,
在这里 我就已经
get ready to do the Fibonacci of N minus 1.
准备好计算(FIB (- N 1))了
So assign to N the difference of the fetch of N and 1.
(ASSIGN N (- (FETCH N) 1))
Now I'm ready to go back to doing the Fib loop.
现在 该跳转到FIB-LOOP了
Do I have... Have I satisfied my contract?
我满足我立下的约定么？
And the answer is yes.
答案是是的
N contains N minus 1, which is what I need.
N现在存储的是N-1 这是我需要的
OK? Continue contains a place I want to go to when I'm done
而CONTINUE包含的是计算完成后 返回的目的地
with calculating FIB N minus 1.
也就是计算(FIB (- N 1))完成之后
So I've satisfied the contract.
因此我满足了这些约定
And therefore, I can write down here a tag, after, a label,
因此 我就可以在这里写下一个标签
after-Fib-N-minus-1.
AFTER-FIB-N-1
Now what am I going to do here?
在这里 我又该做些什么呢？
Here's a place
在这里
where I now have to get ready to do Fib of N minus 2.
我已经准备好去计算(FIB (- N 2))了
But in order to do a Fib of N minus 2,
但是为了计算(FIB (- N 2))
look, I don't know.
首先 我不知道
I've clobbered my N over here.
这里 我已经改变了N
And presumably my N is counted down
或者在这个时候 我的N总是不断地
all the way to 1 or 0 or something at this point.
向1或者0递减
So I don't know what the value of N in the N register is.
所以我不知道N寄存器中存储的到底是什么
I want the value of N that was on the stack
我想要保存在栈中的N的值
that I saved over here
也就是我在这里保存的值
so that could restore it over here.
这样我就可以在这里恢复它
I saved up the value of N,
我在这里存储的N
which is this value of N at this point,
是这个时间点N的值
so that I could restore it after computing Fib of N minus 1,
因此计算完(FIB (- N 1))之后我可以恢复它
so that I could count that down to N minus 2
这样的话 我就可以计算(- N 2)
and then compute Fib of N minus 2.
然后就可以计算(FIB (- N 2))的值
So let's restore that.
现在让我们来恢复它
Restore of N.
(RESTORE N)
Now I'm about to do something which is superstitious,
现在我要做一件很教条的事
and we will remove it shortly.
我们会尽快将其删除
I am about to finish the sequence
如果你们愿意的话
of doing the subroutine call, if you will.
我将要结束子过程调用
I'm going to say, well,
接下来我会说
I also saved up the continuation,
因为我保存了CONTINUE
since I'm going to restore it now.
现在就要去恢复它
But actually, I don't have to,
但实际上 我并不需要这么做
because I'm not going to need it.
因为我并不需要用到它
We'll fix that in a second.
我们稍后会修正它
So we'll do a restore of continue,
现在我们来恢复CONTINUE
which is what I would in general need to do.
通常来说 我都会这么做
And we're just going to see whats called
我们将要看到
what you would call in the compiler world a peephole optimization,
编译器领域中的“窥孔优化”
which says, whoops, you didn't have to do that.
来帮我们消除这个不必要的步骤
OK, so the next thing I see here
因此 我即将要做的就是
is that I have to get ready now to do Fibonacci of N minus 2.
准备好计算(FIB (- N 2))
But I don't have to save N anymore.
但是我不再需要保存N了
The reason why I don't have to save N anymore
原因就是
is because I don't need N after I've done Fib of N minus 2,
计算完(FIB (- N 2))之后 我就不需要N了
because the next thing I do is add.
因为 我接下来要做的就是ADD
So I'm just going to set up my N that way.
因此 我会这么来设置N
Assign N minus difference of fetch N and 2.
(ASSIGN N (- (FETCH N) 2))
Now I have to finish the setup
现在我需要结束
for calling Fibonacci of N minus 2.
调用(FIB (- N 2))的设置过程了
Well, I have to save up continue
我需要保存CONTINUE
and assign continue, continue,
然后把CONTINUE赋值为
to the place which is after Fib N 2,
AFTER-FIB-N-2
that place over here somewhere.
对应了那边代码的某处
However, I've got to be very careful.
然而 我需要非常小心
The old value, the value of Fib of N minus 1,
而(FIB (- N 1))的值
I'm going to need later.
我稍后会用到
The value of Fibonacci of N minus 1,
(FIB (- N 1))的值
I'm going to need.
我需要它的值
And I can't clobber it,
我不能去改变它
because I'm going to have to add it to the value of Fib of N minus 2.
因为我需要用它来加上(FIB (- N 2))
That's in the value register, so I'm going to save it.
它是存放在寄存器中的 因此我需要保存它
So I have to save this right now, save up VAL.
所以现在我要用(SAVE VAL)来保存它
And now I can go off to my subroutine,
现在我就可以调用子过程了
go to Fib loop.
(GOTO FIB-LOOP)
Now before I go any further
现在 在进行更进一步计算之前
and finish this program,
在结束这个程序之前
I just want to look at this segment so far
我想审视一下目前的代码片段
and see, oh yes, there's a sequence of instructions here, if you will
这里有一系列的指令
that I can do something about.
我可以对它们进行某些操作
Here I have a restore of continue,
这里 我有一个操作用来恢复CONTINUE
a save of continue,
一个操作用来保存CONTINUE
and then an assign of continue,
然后给CONTINUE赋值
with no other references to continue in between.
但这之中没有CONTINUE的其它引用
The restore followed by the save
恢复之后又保存
leaves the stack unchanged.
使得栈没有被修改
The only difference is that I set the continue register to a value,
唯一的区别就是 我给CONTINUE寄存器赋了值
which is the value that was on the stack.
一个存放在栈上的值
Since I now clobber that value,
由于我现在改变了这个值
as in it was never referenced,
但这之间并没有引用这个值
these instructions are unnecessary.
这些指令就是不必要的
So we will remove these.
因此我们会移除它们
But I couldn't have seen that unless I had written them down.
但我只有先把它们写出来 才会发现这个情况
Was that really true?
真是这样吗？
Well, I don't know.
我并不知道
OK, so we've now gone off to compute Fibonacci of N minus 2.
现在 我们要开始计算(FIB (- N 2))了
So after that,
计算完毕后
what are we going to do?
我们又要做什么呢？
Well, I suppose the first thing we have to do--
我想 我们首先要做的就是
we've got two things.
我们有两件事要做
We've got a thing in the value register which is now valuable.
目前VAL寄存器中的值 是有意义的
We also have a thing on the stack
然而 栈上也有一个数据
can be restored into the value register.
需要恢复到VAL寄存器中
And what I have to be careful with now
现在我需要非常小心的是
is I want to shuffle this right so I can do the multiply.
正确地给它们排序 以便计算乘法
Now there are various conventions I might use,
现在 我可能会使用不同的约定
but I'm going to be very picky and say,
但我现在会采用非常挑剔的一种
I'm only going to restore into a register I've saved from.
栈上数据来自于哪个寄存器 就恢复到那个寄存器中
If that's the case, I have to do a shuffle here.
如果是这样的话 在这里我就要进行洗牌
It's the same problem with how many hands I have.
这跟我有多少只手是同样的问题
So I'm going to assign to N,
现在我要给N赋值
because I'm not going to need N anymore, N is useless,
因为我现在不再需要N了 N是无用的
the current value of VAL,
获取当前VAL寄存器的值
which was the value of Fib of N minus 2.
也就是(FIB (- N 2))的值
And I'm going to restore the value register now.
现在 我就要恢复VAL寄存器了
This restore matches this save.
这个RESTORE匹配这里的SAVE
And if you're very careful and examine very carefully what goes on,
如果你非常仔细地研究发生了什么
OK? restores and saves are always matched.
会发现 RESTORE和SAVE总是成对的
Now there's an outstanding save,
现在 这里有个额外的SAVE
of course, that we have to get rid of soon.
当然 我们很快就会消灭它
And so I restored the value register.
恢复完VAL寄存器后
Now I restore the continue one,
我就要恢复CONTINUE寄存器了
which matches this one,
它匹配了这个
dot, dot, dot, dot, dot, dot, dot, down to here,
从这里到这里
Now restoring that continuation.
这样就恢复了继续
That continuation is a continuation of Fib of N,
这个表达式继续是由(FIB N)产生的
which is the problem I was trying to solve,
也就是我正尝试求解的
a major problem I'm trying to solve.
最主要的问题
So that's the guy I have to go back to who wants Fib of N.
我需要把(FIB N)的答案返回给这个继续
I saved them all the way up here
在我意识到N并不小于2之前
when I realized N was not less than 2.
我一直保存着它们
And so I had to do a complicated operation.
因此 我需要进行一个复杂的运算
Now I've got everything I need to do it.
现在万事俱备
So I'm going to restore that,
因此我要恢复它们
assign to VAL the sum of fetch VAL and fetch of N
(ASSIGN VAL (+ (FETCH VAL) (FETCH N)))
and go to continue.
然后跳转到CONTINUE
So now I've returned from computing Fibonacci of N,
然后我就从(FIB N)中返回了出来
the general case.
也就是FIB的一般情况
Now what's left is we have to fix up a few details,
现在还有一些细节 需要我们填充
like there's the base case of this induction, immediate answer,
比如归纳的基本情况：可以立即得到答案
as, which is nothing more than
这不过就是
assign to VAL fetch of N,
(ASSIGN VAL (FETCH N)
because N was less than 2,
因为N小于2
and therefore, the answer is N
因此答案就是N
in our original program,
跟源程序是一致的
and return continue--
(GOTO (FETCH CONTINUE))
bobble, bobble almost-- and finally Fib done.
最后就结束了
So that's a fairly complicated program.
这是个相当复杂的程序
And the reason I wanted you see to that
我之所以给你们演示这个程序
is because I want you to see the particular
是因为我想让你们见识
flavors of stack discipline that I was obeying.
我所遵守的栈使用准则
It was first of all, I don't want to save anything
第一点就是 我不想保存那些
that I'm not going to need later.
稍后不需要的值
I was being very careful.
我非常地小心
And it's very important.
这非常重要
And there are all sorts of other disciplines people make
当然 人们还制定了其它的准则
with frames and things like that of some sort,
来操作栈帧之类的东西
where you save all sorts of junk
这些准则中 那些不再需要的东西
you're not going to need later and restore it
也需要保存并恢复
because, in some sense, it's easier to do that.
因为从某种意义上来说 这样做更容易些
That's going to lead to various disasters,
但这会带来各种灾难
which we'll see a little later.
我们稍后就会见识一些
It's crucial to save exactly what you're going to need later.
只保存那些你稍后需要的值 这很关键
It's an important idea.
这是非常重要的理念
And the responsibility of that is whoever saves something
无论谁保存了一个值 都应该由他来恢复
is the guy who restores it, because he needs it.
因为他需要这个值
And in such discipline,
在这样的准则中
you can see what things are unnecessary,
你可以发现哪些数据是不必要的
operations that are unimportant.
哪些操作又是不重要的
Now, one other thing I want to tell you about is very simple
我还想告诉你们
is that, of course, the picture you see is not the whole picture.
当然 你们看到的并不是全部的图景
Supposing I had systems
假设我的系统中
had things like other operations, CAR, CDR, CONS,
具有像CAR、CDR、CONS这样的运算
building a vector
或者创建一个向量
and referencing the nth element of it,
并引用它的第N个元素
or things like that.
等等运算
Well, at this level of detail, whatever it is,
然而 就在这个层次的细节来说
we can conceptualize those as primitive operations in the datapath.
我们可以在数据通路中把它们视为基本运算
In other words, we could say that some machine that, for example, has
换句话说 我们可以认为 有一台机器
has the append machine,
包含了APPEND机器
which has to do cons of the CAR of x
它通过(CONS (CAR X)
with the append of the CDR of x and y,
(APPEND (CDR X) Y)来实现
well, gee, that's exactly the same as the factorial structure.
哦 天啊 这就跟阶乘机器有相同的结构
Well, it's got about the same structure.
当然 它有相同的结构
And what do we have?
我们有什么呢？
We have some sort of things in it
我们有某种东西 其中有
which may be registers, x and y,
诸如X、Y之类的寄存器
and then x has to somehow move to y sometimes,
有时X会移动到Y中
x has to get the value of y.
或者X会取得Y的值
And then we may have to be able to do something which is a cons.
我们或许要需要能够进行CONS运算
I don't remember if I need to like this is in this system,
我记不清这个系统中是否需要这样的东西
but cons is sort of like subtract or add or something.
但CONS有点类似于减法器或加法器之类的东西
It combines two things,
它把两个东西结合起来
producing a thing which is the cons,
然后产生一个序对
which we may then think goes into there.
然后会把输出结果送入到这里
And then maybe a thing called the CAR,
可能还有一个叫做CAR的组件
which will produce-- I can get the CAR or something.
它的结果是 -- 某个东西的CAR部分
And maybe I can get the CDR of something, and so on.
我还可以取得某物的CDR部分 等等
But we shouldn't be too afraid of saying things this way,
但我们不应该害怕这么说
because the worst that could happen
因为最坏的情况不过
is if we open up cons,
当我们打开CONS后
what we're going to find is some machine.
会发现其中存在某台机器
And cons may in fact overlap with CAR and CDR, and it always does,
CONS可能会与CAR和CDR有所重叠
in the same way that plus and minus overlap,
就像加法和减法有所重叠一样
and really the same business.
它们本质上都是一样的
CONS, CAR, and CDR are going to overlap,
CONS、CAR和CDR将会有所重叠
and we're going to find a little controller,
我们会发现其中有小型控制器
a little datapath,
小型的数据通路
which may have some registers in it,
其中还有一些寄存器
some stuff like that.
一些其它的像这样的东西
And maybe inside it,
并且 也许在这之中
there may also be an infinite part,
可能也有无穷的部分
a part that's semi-infinite or something,
又或者是半无穷的 之类的
which is a lot of very uniform stuff,
这些都是统一的东西
which we'll call memory.
也就是我们所谓的“内存”
And I wouldn't be so horrified if that were the way it works.
有限的内存也能无穷地存储 对此我一点也不吃惊
In fact, it does, and we'll talk about that later.
实际上它就是这样的 我们之后就会了解
So are there any questions?
那么 有什么疑问么？
Gee, what an unquestioning audience.
天啊！你们都一言不发
Suppose I tell you a horrible pile of lies.
假设我说得都是谎言吧！
OK.
好吧
Well, thank you.
谢谢大家
Let's take our break.
我们下课吧！
MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
本项目主页
https://github.com/DeathKing/Learning-SICP